Maitraye Das

maitraye.github.io maitraye@u.northwestern.edu

Research Statement

My research interest sits broadly at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessible Computing, with a focus on studying and designing for accessible collaborative content production in ability-diverse teams, i.e., teams involving people with and without disabilities. Methodologically, I take a human-centered, multi-stage approach that involves qualitative studies (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, ethnography) followed by the design, development, and evaluation of new systems through exploratory and mixed-methods experimental analyses. As a first-generation scholar and woman of color from the Global South, my broader goal is to enhance accessibility and inclusion through computing and contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative work.

Education

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

May 2022 (expected)

PhD in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

Dissertation: Augmenting Ability-Diverse Collaboration: Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation by People with Vision Impairments

Committee: Darren Gergle (chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

Mar 2021

MS in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication) *GPA:* 3.97/4.00

0111, 51,7,7, 11,00

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Sep 2015

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) with Honors

GPA: 3.85/4.00 | Rank: 7th in a class of 134 students, magna cum laude

Thesis: Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage

Advisor: Tanzima Hashem

Selected Awards, Honors, & Grants

•	Graduate Research Grant (\$2,999) School of Communication, Northwestern University	2021–2022
•	PhD Student Research Award Department of Computer Science, Northwestern University	2021
•	Best Paper Nomination [C9] ACM Conference of Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS)	2021
•	Best Paper Honorable Mention Award [C8] ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)	2020
•	Finalist (among top 20 students) Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020

- Best Paper Honorable Mention Award [J2]
 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)
- Best Paper Award [C5]
 IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC)
- Best Undergraduate Thesis Award
 Department of Computer Science and Engg., Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology
- Dean's List Award
 Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology
- University Merit Scholarship
 Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology

Journal Articles

- J5. Maitraye Das, Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. 2021. Design and Evaluation of Accessible Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. In ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI), 42 pages. [Impact Factor: 3.15]
- J4. **Maitraye Das,** John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction,* Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183 (April 2021), 30 pages.
- J3. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, Maitraye Das, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS), Vol. 14, 1, Article 5 (March 2021), 30 pages. [Impact Factor: 2.64]
- Q J2. Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends": Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191 (November 2019), 26 pages. [acceptance rate: 31.2%]
 Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions)
 - J1. *Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Maitraye Das, Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and *Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27, (September 2019), pp. 624-642.

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings Papers¹

- C10. **Maitraye Das**, *Thomas McHugh, Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. [On accessibility in collaborative writing]. *Under review (title edited to maintain anonymity).*
- Q C9. Kelly Mack, Maitraye Das, Dhruv Jain, Danielle Bragg, John Tang, Andrew Begel, Erin Beneteau, Josh Urban Davis, Abraham Glasser, Joon Sung Park, and Venkatesh Potluri. 2021. Mixed Abilities and

_

^{*} Directly mentored student.

¹ <u>Top-tier venues in Human-Computer Interaction</u> include extensively peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI. These highly selective conferences are intended for archival papers and <u>comparable to journals in visibility, selectively, and impact</u>. When available, the acceptance rate is included.

- Varied Experiences: A Group Autoethnography of a Virtual Summer Internship. In the 23rd International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS '21), 21 pages. Best Paper Nomination [acceptance rate: 29%]
- **Q** C8. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20),* 1-15. [acceptance rate: 24.3%] **Best Paper Honorable Mention** (Top 5% of submissions).
 - C7. **Maitraye Das,** Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563, 14 pages. [acceptance rate: 23.8%]
 - C6. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, **Maitraye Das**, Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart Technology. In *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18)*, Paper 102, 1-16. [acceptance rate: 25%]
- C5. Maitraye Das, *Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, *Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem. 2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42nd IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC '18), pp. 645-654. [acceptance rate: 24%]

 Best Paper Award
 - C4. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das**. 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20th IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*, pp. 1-6.
 - C3. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*, pp. 510-515.
 - C2. *Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and *Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth platform to combat health hazards of women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16)*.
 - C1. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '16)*, pp. 201-206.

Conference Extended Abstracts, Workshop Papers, and Posters

- W8 **Maitraye Das.** 2021. Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In *Human Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC '21)*.
- W7. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In 2020 Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW '20). [Doctoral Consortium]

- W6. Maitraye Das, Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In the Workshop "Nothing About Us Without Us": Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI).
- W5. **Maitraye Das.** 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In the *Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media, ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing (CSCW '19).*
- W4. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In *Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18)*, pp. 1744-1749.
- W3. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing (GHC)*, USA.
- W2. **Maitraye Das**, Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- W1. Maitraye Das, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. In Grace Hopper Celebration India (GHCI).
 Best Technical Poster Award

Research Experience

Northwestern University | Collaborative Technology Lab

Fall 2017 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Darren Gergle

- Conducted contextual interviews and observations to understand collaborative writing practices and accessibility needs of blind professionals. Built new accessible systems to support blind writers in asynchronous and synchronous collaborative writing. Evaluated systems through a design exploration study with 15 blind writers and a mixed-methods controlled experiment with 48 blind writers. Faculty collaborator: Anne Marie Piper
- Collected a dataset of nearly 0.45 billion edits by 2000 OpenStreetMap editors using Python and Osmium. Performed quantitative analysis to investigate gender-based self-focus bias in OpenStreetMap. Faculty collaborator: Brent Hecht

Northwestern University | Inclusive Technology Lab

Spring 2018 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Anne Marie Piper

Conducted ethnographic field observations and contextual interviews at a weaving studio for people
with vision impairments. Designed an audio-enhanced loom to support blind weavers in performing
weaving and an audio-tactile system to support accessible drafting of fabric patterns.

Microsoft Research (MSR), USA | Ability Team

Summer 2020

Research Intern | mentored by John Tang

- Conducted semi-structured interviews with 36 neurodivergent professionals. Outlined practical
 guidelines for inclusive organizational practices and accessible design of remote collaboration tools.
 Faculty collaborators: Kathryn E. Ringland, Anne Marie Piper
- Performed a group autoethnographic study reflecting on accessible practices in an ability-diverse team
 and highlighted opportunities for designing technologies for accessible remote work.
 MSR collaborators: Danielle Bragg, Andrew Begel

Western Washington University, USA

Summer 2017

Researcher (remote) | mentored by Moushumi Sharmin and Shameem Ahmed

Performed a systematic literature review on smart technologies for children on the autism spectrum.

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Aug 2014 - Sep 2017

Undergraduate Researcher | advised by Tanzima Hashem

Developed a secret-sharing algorithm for privacy-preserving disease risk queries in genomic databases.

Teaching Experience

University of Washington | Information School

Fall 2020

Guest lecturer | Input and Interaction (INFO 463)

 Delivered talk on accessibility in collaborative writing, prepared prompts for small group discussions, and led the larger group discussion. Paper [J2] was a required reading for the class.

United International University (UIU), Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct 2015 - Mar 2017

Lecturer/Instructor | Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

CSE 313 – Computer Architecture

Delivered lectures, held weekly office hours, and designed and evaluated assignments and final exams. Fall 2015: 29 students

CSE 225 – Digital Logic Design

Delivered lectures, held weekly office hours, and designed and evaluated assignments and final exams. Fall 2015: 27 students; Summer 2016: 26 students; Fall 2016: 54 students in two classes

CSE 226 – Digital Logic Design Laboratory

Delivered lectures, conducted lab sessions, and supervised and evaluated term projects.

Fall 2015: 77 students in three classes; Spring 2016: 29 students; Summer 2016: 49 students in two classes; Fall 2016: 40 students in two classes

CSE 236 – Assembly programming laboratory

Delivered lectures, conducted lab sessions, and designed and graded weekly assignments and quizzes. Spring 2016: 15 students; Summer 2016: 29 students

CSE 113 – Electrical Circuits

Delivered lectures, held weekly office hours, and designed and evaluated assignments and final exams. Spring 2016: 67 students in two classes; Summer 2016: 18 students; Fall 2016: 31 students

Course Designed

Accessible Collaboration | Northwestern University

Mar 2021

Completed as one of the PhD qualifying exams | Supervised by Darren Gergle

 Designed the curriculum of a Computer Science/Communication upper-level undergraduate course on accessibility in collaborative work. Planned class structure, reading materials, assignments, projects, and assessments following the universal design for learning and active learning guidelines.

Mentoring Experience

- Thomas McHugh | Computer Science undergrad, Northwestern University 2020 Present Coauthored paper: [C10]. Own the first place at the ACM Student Research Competition (SRC) at ASSETS 2020 and SRC Grand Finals 2021. Next position: Software engineer at Apple.
- Evan Li | Mechanical Engineering MS program, Northwestern University
 Mentored on designing an audio-enhanced loom for accessible weaving.
- Rawan Mohamed | Computer Science undergrad, Northwestern University
 Mentored on performing qualitative coding on user evaluation data.
- Caroline Brewley | High school student researcher
 Mentored on performing a literature review and design sketching low-fidelity prototypes.
- Dana Choi | Statistics and Economics undergrad, Northwestern University
 Mentored on data labeling for the OpenStreetMap gender bias project.
- Oliver Baldwin | Computer Science and Statistics undergrad, Northwestern University
 Mentored on data labeling for the OpenStreetMap gender bias project.
- Nusrat Jahan Mazumder | Computer Science undergrad, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech
 Coauthored papers: [J1] and [C5]. Next position: PhD student at University of Virginia.
- Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar | Computer Science undergrad, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech
 Coauthored papers: [J1] and [C5]. Next position: PhD student at University of Texas at Dallas.
- Fatema Khan | Computer Science undergrad, United International University
 Coauthored papers: [C2] and a poster for GHC'17. Next position: Lecturer at Prime Asia University.
- Ahiya Ahammed | Computer Science undergrad, United International University
 Coauthored paper: [C2]. Next position: PhD student at University of Debrecen, Hungary.

Other Awards and Grants

Grace Hopper Celebration India

- Selected for EECS Rising Stars Workshop
 Organized by Massachusetts Institute of Technology
- Special Recognition for Outstanding Review
 ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 3 times
 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work & Social Computing
 2021, 2019
- Conference Travel Grant
 Northwestern University (\$2,300 + \$1,500)
 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (\$600)
 2018
- Student Scholarship
 Grace Hopper Celebration USA
 Grace Hopper Celebration India
- Best Technical Poster [W1]

2014

Invited Talks, Panels, and Demonstrations

InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University

•	Accessibility, HCI, and Aging (AHA) research group University of Michigan Talk: Designing for ability-diverse collaboration	Nov 2021 (scheduled)	
•	Center for Research and Education on Accessible Technology and Experiences (University of Washington Talk: Designing for ability-diverse collaboration	(CREATE) Oct 2021 (scheduled)	
•	Workshop on The Future of Care Work ACM CSCW Discussion topic: Rethinking power and politics in care work within ability-dive	Oct 2021 (scheduled) rrse maker communities	
•	Microsoft Office and Windows Accessibility Teams Microsoft Talk: Understanding accessibility in collaborative writing for people with vision	Feb 2021 impairments	
•	New Future of Work Group Meeting Microsoft Talk: Understanding accessibility in remote work for neurodivergent professions	Sep 2020	
•	Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group, Virtual Event Talk: Designing for accessible interaction	Apr 2020	
•	PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA, US. Poster: Designing for collaborative content creation for people with vision impa		
•	TSB Prospective PhD Students Visiting Weekend Northwestern University Panel discussions on graduate life and research at Northwestern Demonstrations on accessible collaborative writing and weaving	2021, 2018 2019	
Ac	ademic Services		
	ogram Committee Member		
	adow PC, ACM COMPASS	2021	
Gr	ace Hopper Celebration, HCI Track	2021	
Re	viewer		
ACM CHI [*outstanding review recognitions: 3] 2021 - 2022			
	CM CSCW [*outstanding review recognitions: 2]	2019 - 2021	
	CM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS)	2021	
	EE COMPSAC	2021	
	CM DIS	2020 2017	
	ace Hopper Celebration stralasian Database Conference	2017	
114	Straiasian Database Conference	2010	
Sti	udent Volunteer		
	CM CHI	2019, 2021	
	CM CSCW	2019	
ACM UbiComp			
Inf	SoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2018	
Pu	blicity Co-chair		
т /		2010	

2019

Outreach & Memberships

Co-host & Co-organizer	
Inspiring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM)	2020 - Present
Member	
Northwestern Graduate Women in Computing	2019 - Present
Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)	2017 - Present
Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction (SIGCHI)	2017 – Present
Special Interest Group on Accessible Computing (SIGACCESS)	2017 - Present
Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering	2015 – Present
Code Coach Volunteer	
BraveCamp Chicago (non-profit coding camp for high school girls)	Summer 2018
Vice-President	
Murchhona: BUET (cultural club)	2014 - 2015

References

Darren Gergle

John G. Searle Professor

Department of Communication Studies and Department of Computer Science (by courtesy)

Northwestern University.

Email: dgergle@northwestern.edu

Anne Marie Piper

Associate Professor

Department of Informatics

University of California, Irvine.

Email: ampiper@uci.edu

Brent Hecht

Associate Professor

Department of Computer Science and School of Communication

Northwestern University.

Email: bhectht@northwestern.edu